New GST rates have been implemented in the country
and the huge benefit is being seen in many sectors
and one of them
is insurance because now the government has reduced the
GST rates on the insurance sector to
zero.  That means,
if you have taken any insurance till now, the
GST you were paying on it has now become zero.  To
discuss this in detail,
we have with us CV Pandey ji,
who is an insurance advisor and is
associated with many different companies including LIC.
First of all, a very warm welcome to CV
Pandey ji.  Sir, first of all I would like to know from you
how do you see the impact of making it 0% on the insurance sector
?  How much benefit will common customers get from
this?   The
common customer is getting full benefit of the GST that used to be levied,
sir.  When GST was zero, the
premium used to be higher.
Now that GST has been removed, its premium has reduced.  The
common customer benefits a lot from it.   There
is definitely a benefit.  But if there are
some questions in the minds of common people that
the way we take any policy, then
suppose there is a policy of Rs 1 lakh.
Suppose there was 18% GST on it, which has now been reduced to zero.
So in such a situation, the premium
amount was simply the premium after deduction of 18% GST,
only the premium remained.  Only the
premium is left sir, the GST of 18% which used to be levied has
now become zero, so the
customer will have to pay only the premium and the GST has been
removed, the government has removed it, so
he will not have to pay it now,
what will happen to him because of this, his premium will become cheaper,
his premium will reduce,
what is his burden of paying the premium, he used to
think many times that it is so much
premium, can I pay it or not and I will have to
pay it every year, so now he feels that if
18% has been reduced then I can take it
and I can afford it.
Sir, if we understand this as an example,
if someone has a policy of Rs 1 lakh, if
someone is 35 years old and is getting the policy
done, then please explain a little about how the entire mathematics
works out, for example.
Sir, if
the customer is 35 years old
and he takes a life insurance policy, then
if he takes a life insurance policy
and puts a sum insured of 5 lakhs, then
earlier the premium for a sum insured of 5 lakhs used to be
₹3591
and plus GST of ₹1618, it would become
₹3759,
now after the removal of GST, and in the second year,
his premium would be ₹3760 on the
same ₹5 lakhs because the GST levied on life insurance was
earlier 4.5% in the first year
and 2.5% in the second year, so his
premium got reduced.  Now, if a person
takes a policy of Rs 5 lakh and
is 35 years old, then his
premium has now become ₹35,951
in the first year as well and in the second year onward, the
entire premium will remain ₹35,951 only
up to maturity.  So this is a big relief that has been
received from this GST reform.  But
apart from this, Sir, there are some questions also that suppose
someone has paid the premium recently.
Suppose if I talk about myself, I
paid a premium in the month of July, on which
I would have obviously paid GST as well
and now that these
new rules have come from the government, they will come into effect from 22nd September.
So could that GST money have been refunded
?
Sir, we need clarity from the government on this.   Will
the government return the money or not?
Because the tax has been paid and
if the tax on GST has been paid then
if the government gives clarity that yes we will
return this money then it will be returned and if the
payment is not returned then it will not be returned
but from next year it may happen that
you may not have to pay GST on your renewal premium next year.  It is
quite obvious that as per the new rules, from
now onwards, all the customers who will
join and want to get their policy done will
not have to pay GST
and because of this, since you
also give such advice and are also an insurance advisor, there will be
many customers around you who will be
waiting for the
slight exemption due to GST reforms and
they will wait for that.  There must be many such customers,
sir.  There are a lot of customers.
Many people were waiting for GST ever since the Prime Minister announced it from the Red Fort
and we ourselves have
some 10 to 15 customers who are saying
that they will do it after there is clarity on GST.
So now there is clarity on GST.
So now they are saying
that after 22nd when the new rate will come, then
we will pay the premium.  I wo
n't do it before that.  Although the announcement made by the Prime Minister was on
15th August,
from the ramparts of the Red Fort, he had announced
that on Diwali you are going to get a
big gift and since then a
little slowdown was seen in the insurance sector
because many
customers thought that once
this announcement is made, we will get some benefit and
after that we will see, there was a
similar trend in many sectors, whether it is the auto sector
or FMCG,
products were not being purchased on a large scale
and people were hopeful that they will get the
benefit of this reform
in the coming time.  Hence, the
same thing has been seen in insurance also.
Thank you very much Pandey Sir for talking to us.
So a big decision has been taken by the government in the insurance sector.
Certainly, this announcement will
directly benefit the customers.  But will you get
back the GST you have paid first
or not?  No clear comment has been made by the government on this yet.
However, from now onwards,
if you get any insurance done after September 22,
you will
not have to pay any GST.  This is a big update.
What is your opinion on this whole news?  You
can definitely tell us by commenting and stay connected
with Jharkhand Business.
[music]